<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<kiln:root xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
           xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
           xmlns:kiln="http://www.kcl.ac.uk/artshums/depts/ddh/kiln/ns/1.0"
           xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform">

  <xsl:import href="cocoon://_internal/template/xsl/stylesheets/text-file-list-to-html.xsl" />

  <!-- Type of document (name of subdirectory containing the source
       file). -->
  <xsl:variable name="document_type" select="'epidoc'" />
  <!-- ID of sitemap map:match to use for display of individual
       texts. -->
  <xsl:variable name="match_id" select="'local-epidoc-display-html'" />

  <kiln:parent>
    <xi:include href="works.xml" />
  </kiln:parent>

  <kiln:child>
    <kiln:block name="title">
      <kiln:super />
      <xsl:text>Documents</xsl:text>
    </kiln:block>

    <kiln:block name="page-heading">
      <kiln:super />
      <xsl:text>Documents</xsl:text>
    </kiln:block>

    <kiln:block name="content">
      <div class="row">
        <div class="large-12 columns">
          <p>Total items: <xsl:value-of select="count(collection(concat('file:',system-property('user.dir'),'/webapps/ROOT/content/xml/epidoc/?select=*.xml;recurse=yes')))"/></p>
          <p>The study of fiscal estates relies on the analysis of the structure of the surviving documentation, and of the logic that underpinned its production and transmission. <i>FISCUS</i> has been designed in order to fulfil this objective; the project either singled out specific documentary sets, which provide information on fiscal assets (and on the prerogatives connected to them), or else entailed the complete survey of important archival collections.</p>
          <p>The documents are listed – under the heading ‘Title’ – according to their archival shelf-mark; when it has not been possible to satisfactorily identify it, the main edition has been recorded. The field ‘Record Source’ specifies whether the marking-up of the primary sources has been carried out on the basis of the text of an unpublished document, of its edition (critical or not), of its summary (<i>regesto</i>), or else thanks to the information drawn from the secondary literature. Specific attention has been paid to the tradition of each document marked-up in the database (cf. the field ‘Document Tradition’). Please note that under the category of ‘Uncertain Tradition’ one can find both forgeries and documents containing interpolations. If one document has survived only in later copies, its ‘Date/Period of Redaction’ has been indicated. The field ‘Provenance’ refers to the former storage location of one document (if this is different from the current one). The field ‘Fiscal Property’ indicates whether the document provides information on estates belonging to the fiscal domain or not (‘Uncertain’ means that, at present, no definitive answer can be given).</p>
          
          <!--<p>The source EpiDoc XML for all of the listed documents are available in a <a href="{kiln:url-for-match('local-epidoc-zip', ($language), 0)}">ZIP archive</a>.</p>-->

          <xsl:apply-templates mode="text-index"
            select="/aggregation/response/result" />
        </div>
      </div>
    </kiln:block>
  </kiln:child>
</kiln:root>
