<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>About</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Fiscus</authority>
                <idno type="filename">About</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative
                        Commons Attributions-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="commentary" xml:id="about">
                <div>
                    <p>As already stated in the Homepage, <title>FISCUS</title> does not set out to provide the readers with a critical edition of the texts that have been uploaded. First-level records have in fact been created, sometimes, from the worksheets that individual researchers collected for their own studies. Indeed, the number of records and the mark up can be – and will be – implemented; the database is a work-in-progress which has reached only a first stage of completion.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div>
                    <head>Alma Mater Studiorum – Università di Bologna e Università degli Studi di Torino</head>
                    <p>The research units based in Bologna and Turin have marked up the following documentary sets:</p>
                    <p>1) the royal diplomas addressed to religious and ecclesiastical institutions and to laypeople in the Kingdom of Italy. In more detail, the researchers involved in these two units have identified and tagged: 1.1) the diplomas issued by Emperor Lothar I; 1.2) the diplomas granted by the so-called italic kings; 1.3) the diplomas issued by Emperor Otto III. The reasons for this choice lie in the fact that Lothar I devoted a significative amount of his legislative efforts to the management of the royal domain in Italy, and to the strengthening of the Carolingian rule in the peninsula. The italic kings have been generally – but wrongly – regarded by the historiography as weak rulers, who were not capable to run a state and therefore turned fiscal estates into provate properties. Otto III, then, centred its politics – which often go under the label of <foreign>renovatio imperii</foreign> – around the management of the royal domain and the prerogatives connected to it. Other diplomas can be found in the database, especially if they have some type of link to the emperors and kings mentioned above, or if they are connected to the monasteries and churches enumerated at point 2.</p> 
                    <div type="hidden">    
                    <p>2) the documents produced by – and once preserved in the archives of – the royal monasteries that have been selected as the project’s case-studies. Those archival series have not been put into the database in their entirety; documents have been selected so as to illuminate specific patterns in the history of the royal domain. The mark up has been carried out on both published and unpublished texts. Thus, the reader will find charters from S. Benedetto di Polirone (marked up by Beatrice Ferretti), S. Maria di Pomposa (marked up by Chiara Stedile), S. Salvatore/S. Giulia di Brescia (marked up by Tiziana Lazzari), S. Salvatore al Monte Amiata (marked up by Chiara Stedile and Lorenzo Tabarrini), S. Silvestro di Nonantola (marked up by Edoardo Manarini), S. Sisto di Piacenza (marked up by Lorenzo Tabarrini and Evelina del Mercato). To these we need to add the bishoprics of Novara and Vercelli (marked up by Caterina Ciccopiedi).</p>
                    </div>
                    <anchor type="expand-collapse-button"/>
                </div>
                
                <div>
                    <head>Università di Pisa</head>
                    <p>The research unit based in Pisa has proceeded to the systematic mark up of some of the most important archival series of Tuscany – in terms of both the overall number of documents that have been preserved, and the continuity of the series over time. The main objectives can be summarised as follows: to shed light on what can be considered as the voids of the surviving documentation – that is to say, on the geographical areas that, paradoxically, are not enlightened by a documentation which is otherwise very rich; and to underscore the importance of often-neglected and seemingly-marginal pieces of information, such as the lists of land borders or topical dates.</p>
                    <div type="hidden">
                        <p>These two research avenues have proven particularly fruitful, especially if one looks at the Lucchese documentary materials; in more detail, those preserved in the Archivio Storico Diocesano (starting in the eighth century) and the Archivio di Stato (from the eleventh century onwards). In addition to Lucca and the Lucchesia, the Maremma region has been investigated. Both regions have been the object of extensive research over the years, but their sources had never been gathered in a XML-based database before.</p>
                        <p>Here follows the list of the groups of documents that have been selected and marked up so far:</p>
                        <p>1) the main documents regarding fiscal lands in the political space under the direct control of the duke of Lucca and marquis of <foreign>Tuscia</foreign>, the overarching public authority in the region; these are only a few, however, as he did not issue any diploma until the second quarter of the eleventh century;</p>
                        <p>2) from Lucca, evenly-distributed groups of documents dating to the eighth century (from the Archivio Storico Diocesano, marked up by Simone Collavini), the ninth (from the Archivio Storico Diocesano, marked up by Mattia Viti), the tenth (from the Archivio Storico Diocesano, marked up by Paolo Tomei), the eleventh (from the Archivio di Stato, marked up by Luca Angeli), and the twelfth (from the Archivio di Stato, especially the parchments from the Ospedale di Altopascio, marked up by Alessandro Giacomelli);</p>
                        <p>3) the chartulary of the monastery of S. Quirico di Populonia, along with other parchments regarding the Maremma region, especially those preserved in the <foreign>fondi</foreign> Città di Massa, Legato Bichi Borghesi, S. Agostino in the Archivio di Stato di Siena (in which one can find the charters that were previously preserved in the monasteries of S. Pietro di Monteverdi, S. Bartolomeo di Sestinga, and S. Antimo in val di Starcia).</p>
                        <p>In addition to this, Loris Motta (PhD candidate) has marked up the documents regarding some of the areas he was studying for his thesis; namely, the borders between northern-eastern Piedmont and Lomellina, as well as the counties of Pombia, Vercelli, Ossola, Bulgaria and Lomello. He paid particular attention to the so-called Rotolo dei Diplomi in the Archivio Storico Diocesano in Novara, covering the reign of Berengar I. To this, a small documentary corpus regarding King Arduino d’Ivrea and the abbey of Fruttuaria has to be added.</p>
                    </div>
                    <anchor type="expand-collapse-button"/>
                </div>
                
                <div>
                    <head>Università degli Studi Roma Tre</head>
                    <p>The research unit based in Rome set out to mark up the documents regarding the landed transactions which involved papal estates in the Latium region, as they have been recorded – in abbreviated form – by Cardinal Deusdedit between <foreign>c.</foreign> 1083 and <foreign>c.</foreign> 1087 within his <foreign>Collectio Canonum</foreign>. In addition, the earliest papal privileges preserved in the ecclesiastical archives of Rome, and dating to the ninth century, have been equally marked up. This part of the research has been carried out by Dario Internullo.</p>
                    <div type="hidden">
                        <p>Southern Italy has been investigated, too. In particular, the reader will find:</p>
                    <p>1) the documents issued by Lombard rulers (and marked up by Vito Loré and Paola Massa) in the duchies-principalities of Benevento, Capua and Salerno. Namely, those preserved in the Biblioteca Capitolare and the Museo del Sannio (Benevento); the monastery of Montevergine (Avellino); the abbey of SS. Trinità di Cava de’ Tirreni (Salerno); the Archivio di Stato and Archivio Diocesano in Salerno; the Archivio di Stato and the Biblioteca Napoletana di Storia Patria (Napoli); the Archivio Apostolico and the Biblioteca Vaticana (Città del Vaticano); and finally, one will also find the later copies contained in literary works, such as the <foreign>Chronicon Sanctae Sophiae</foreign> and the <foreign>Catalogus Baronum</foreign>;</p>
                    <p>2) the chartularies of the monasteries of Montecassino and S. Vincenzo al Volturno, to which one needs to add the published charters of Montecassino dating to the Lombard period, from the ninth to the eleventh century (marked up by Antonio Tagliente and Giulia Zornetta);</p>
                    <p>3) diplomas granted by (and other documents testifying to the presence of) the Norman princes (marked up by Valerio De Angelis) dating to the period that stretches from the conquest of the principality on the part of Norman armies to the inclusion – however imperfect – of the principality into the Norman Kingdom (those charters have already been identified and listed by Graham Loud); to these we need to add one diploma issued by Emperor Conrad III in 1144, in which Roberto II of Capua – who had been exiled – features as a witness.</p>
                    </div>
                    <anchor type="expand-collapse-button"/>
                </div>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
